Md. Shovon Biswas

I am a software engineer at Gigatech Limited in Bangladesh. My expertise in front-end software development is extensive, and I work with Angular, Typescript, Javascript, and other technologies such as Docker, Jenkins, and Kubernetes. I also worked in Python and Django as an intern. In addition, I am also experienced in AI software development, deep learning, and machine learning. Though I am a software developer, I have also conducted computer vision research. I've currently published three papers and am working on more.

Education

2018- 2022

B.SC, Bangladesh University of Business & Technology (BUBT).

Thesis title: A Deep Learning Based Smartphone Application for Detecting Mango Diseases and Pesticide Suggestions.

Result: 3.74 out of 4.

Employment History

2022 - Continue

Software Engineer: Gigatech Limited, Bangladesh's Dhaka, Gulshan-1. I worked on numerous Fintech (Electronic Know Your Customer) eKYC solutions for institutions including BRAC Bank, HSBC Bank, NRBC Bank, Prime Bank, and others as a software engineer at Gigatech Limited. It also includes certain Saas solutions, such as "Jachai," to which I also made contributions. The process of electronically confirming a customer's identification in the banking industry, known as eKYC, is usually carried out in accordance with regulatory requirements. It is a digital process that replaces the conventional, paper-based KYC (Know Your Customer) procedure, which makes it more rapid, secure, and effective. Using my frontend and backend skills was part of my job. My work included the use of HTML, CSS, Angular, Typescript, Javascript, Bootstrap, and Tailwind CSS. I utilized Python, C#, and DotNet for the backend. Not only I used these things but also I used Docker, Kubernetes, and Jenkins.

2022 - 2022

Backend Engineer. Gigatech Limited, Gulshan-1, Dhaka, Bangladesh. I began my career in Python as a backend developer. In the beginning of my career, I designed and maintained server-side web application logic in Python, concentrating on backend components, using Django. In order to improve efficiency, I integrated the MySQL database and optimized the request process. I also established an internal coffee management system API. additionally learned about machine learning (ML) and artificial intelligence (AI).

2021 - 2022

Freelance Instructor. I used to work as a freelance Python instructor while I was a student. I created and taught specialized Python programming courses to a wide range of students, from beginners to intermediates, while working as a freelance Python instructor. I created comprehensive lessons and practical exercises to cover fundamental subjects including object-oriented programming, data structures, Python syntax, and well-known libraries like Pandas and NumPy.

Area of Research Interest

Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Natural language processing (LLM, Generative AI, Text Analysis), Image Processing (Classification, Object Detection, Medical Image Analysis), Cyber-security, Cognitive AI, Explainable artificial intelligence (XAI)

Research Publications

Journal Articles

M. Rahaman, M. Chowdhury, M. A. Rahman, *et al.*, "A deep learning based smartphone application for detecting mango diseases and pesticide suggestions," *International Journal of Computing and Digital Systems*, vol. 13, no. 1, pp. 1–1, 2023.

Conference Papers

- M. N. Rahaman, S. Chaki, M. S. Biswas, et al., "Identifying the signature of suicidality: A machine learning approach," in THEETAS 2022: Proceedings of The International Conference on Emerging Trends in Artificial Intelligence and Smart Systems, THEETAS 2022, 16-17 April 2022, European Alliance for Innovation, 2022, p. 279.
- M. N. Rahaman, M. S. Biswas, S. Chaki, M. M. Hossain, S. Ahmed, and M. Biswas, "Lane detection for autonomous vehicle management: Pht approach," in 2021 24th International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT), IEEE, 2021, pp. 1–6.

Skills

Languages | English, Bengali.

Coding Javascript, Typescript, Python, C#, C, C++, Java.

Databases Mysql, Oracle.

Web Dev HTML, css, Bootstrap, Tailwind CSS, JavaScript, Typescript, Angular, ReactJs, Django, Django REST_FramWork, React-Native.

PaaS & IaaS. Docker, Kubernetes, Jenkins.

Pado & Idao. Docker, Rubernetes, Jenkins.

Machine Learning Supervised Learning (Regression, Classification), Unsupervised Learning (Clustering), Deep Learning (ANN, CNN, RNN, LSTM, Transfer Learning), NLP.

Misc. Microsoft Office, La Verleaf, Android Studio, Anaconda, Pycharm, Intellij, VS-code, Google Coolab

Talks

Virtual

In Proceedings of 24th International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT), Dhaka, Bangladesh: Presented our research paper. Lane Detection for Autonomous Vehicle Management: PHT Approach.